Ah yes, those university days,
صحيح , تلك أيام الجامعة
a heady mix of Ph.D-level pure mathematics
خلط ثقيل بين درجة الدكتوراة والرياضيات البحتة
and world debating championships,
والعالم يناقش البطولات
or, as I like to say, "Hello, ladies. Oh yeah."
أو كما أحب أن اقول : أهلاً بالسيدات
Didn't get much sexier than the Spence
لن تكون أكثر جنسية من سبنس
at university, let me tell you.
في الجامعة، اسمحوا لي أن أقول لكم.
It is such a thrill for a humble breakfast radio announcer
أنه لشيء مثير للحماس فطور مذيع راديو متواضع
from Sydney, Australia, to be here on the TED stage
من سيدني، أستراليا، تكون هنا على خشبة المسرح تيد
literally on the other side of the world.
حرفيا على الجانب الآخر من العالم.
And I wanted to let you know, a lot of the things you've heard
وأردت أن أخبركم أن الكثير من الأشياء التي سمعتموها
about Australians are true.
حول الأستراليين صحيحة.
From the youngest of ages, we display
من أصغر الاعمار ونحن نقوم بعرض
a prodigious sporting talent.
مواهب رياضية مذهلة.
On the field of battle, we are brave and noble warriors.
في ميدان المعركة، ونحن المحاربين شجعان ونبلاء.
What you've heard is true.
ما سمعته صحيح.
Australians, we don't mind a bit of a drink,
الأستراليين، نحن لا نمانع قليلاً من الشراب
sometimes to excess, leading to embarrassing social situations. (Laughter)
تزود قليلاً في بعض الأحيان، مما يؤدي إلى حالات اجتماعية محرجة.
This is my father's work Christmas party, December 1973.
هذا هو عمل والدي في حفلة عيد الميلاد، ديسمبر 1973.
I'm almost five years old. Fair to say,
كان عمري خمس سنوات. لأكون صادقاً
I'm enjoying the day a lot more than Santa was.
أنا استمتع اليوم أكثر بكثير مما كان سانتا.
But I stand before you today
ولكن أنا أقف أمامكم اليوم
not as a breakfast radio host,
ليس كمذيع راديو صباحي
not as a comedian, but as someone who was, is,
ليس كممثل كوميدي، ولكن كشخص كان ولازال
and always will be a mathematician.
وسوف يكون دائماً عالم رياضيات.
And anyone who's been bitten by the numbers bug
وأي شخص تلقى عضة من حشرات الأرقام
knows that it bites early and it bites deep.
يعرف أن أنه لدغ مبكرا وأنه لدغ عميقاً.
I cast my mind back when I was in second grade
رجعت بذهني إلى الوراء عندما كنت في الصف الثاني
at a beautiful little government-run school
في مدرسة صغيرة جميلة تديرها الحكومة
called Boronia Park in the suburbs of Sydney,
اسمها بروني بارك في ضواحي سيدني،
and as we came up towards lunchtime, our teacher,
وعندما جاء وقت الغداء، معلمتنا
Ms. Russell, said to the class,
السيدة راسل قالت للصف
"Hey, year two. What do you want to do after lunch?
"لحظة، السنة الثانية. ماذا تريدون أن تفعلوا بعد الغداء؟
I've got no plans."
ليس لدينا خطة
It was an exercise in democratic schooling,
أنها كانت ممارسة في التعليم المدرسي الديمقراطي
and I am all for democratic schooling, but we were only seven.
وأنا كلياً للتعليم المدرسي الديمقراطي، ولكننا كنا سبعة فقط.
So some of the suggestions we made as to what
حتى أن بعض الاقتراحات التي اقترحناها فيما يتعلق
we might want to do after lunch were a little bit impractical,
بماذا نمكن ان نفعل بعد الغداء كانت نوعاً ما غير عملية
and after a while, someone made a particularly silly suggestion
وبعد فترة من الوقت، قدم شخص اقتراحاً سخيفاً
and Ms. Russell patted them down with that gentle aphorism,
والسيدة راسيل دعته للجلوس وهي تقول المقولة المشهورة
"That wouldn't work.
"هذا لن يجدي.
That'd be like trying to put a square peg through a round hole."
سيكون ذلك أشبه بمحاولة لوضع سدادة مربعة في ثقب مدور "
Now I wasn't trying to be smart.
أنا لم أكن أحاول أن أكون ذكياً.
I wasn't trying to be funny.
لم أكن أحاول أن أكون مضحكا.
I just politely raised my hand,
ولكن رفعت يدي بكل أدب
and when Ms. Russell acknowledged me, I said,
وعندما سمحت السيدة راسل لي بالحديث، قلت:
in front of my year two classmates, and I quote,
أمام زملائي من الصف الثاني، وأنا اقتبس،
"But Miss,
"لكن سيدتي،
surely if the diagonal of the square
بالتأكيد إذا كان قطري المربع
is less than the diameter of the circle,
أقل من قطر الدائرة،
well, the square peg will pass quite easily through the round hole."
السدادة المربعة ستمر بسهولة تامة عن طريق الفتحه المستديرة. "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"It'd be like putting a piece of toast through a basketball hoop, wouldn't it?"
"أنه مثل وضع قطعة خبز التوست خلال شبكة السلة، أليس كذلك؟"
And there was that same awkward silence
ثم عم الصمت الغريب
from most of my classmates,
من معظم زملائي،
until sitting next to me, one of my friends,
حتى أحد أصدقائي الذي يجلس بجواري
one of the cool kids in class, Steven, leaned across
واحد من الأطفال ، ستيفن، توجه نحوي
and punched me really hard in the head.
ولكمني على وجهي بقوة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now what Steven was saying was, "Look, Adam,
ما كان يقوله ستيفن ، "أسمع، آدم،
you are at a critical juncture in your life here, my friend.
أنت في مرحلة خطيرة في حياتك هنا، يا صديقي.
You can keep sitting here with us.
يمكنك أن تبقى جالس هنا معنا.
Any more of that sort of talk, you've got to go and sit
أي نوع آخر من هذا الحديث، سيجب عليك أن تذهب وتجلس
over there with them."
معهم هناك ".
I thought about it for a nanosecond.
فكرت في ذلك في وهلة
I took one look at the road map of life,
أخذت نظرة واحدة إلى خارطة الطريق للحياة،
and I ran off down the street marked "Geek"
ورحت أركض خارجاً على شارع مسمى بـ الهوس
as fast as my chubby, asthmatic little legs would carry me.
كسرعة رجلي السمينة والمتأزمة التي بإمكانها ان تحملني
I fell in love with mathematics from the earliest of ages.
سقطت في حب رياضيات في عمر مبكر
I explained it to all my friends. Maths is beautiful.
وأوضحت لجميع أصدقائي. أن الرياضيات جميلة.
It's natural. It's everywhere.
أنه أمر طبيعي. في كل مكان.
Numbers are the musical notes
هي أرقام الملاحظات الموسيقية
with which the symphony of the universe is written.
مع ما يكتب بها سيمفونية الكون.
The great Descartes said something quite similar.
قال ديكارت العظيم شيء مماثل تماما.
The universe "is written in the mathematical language."
الكون "مكتوب بلغة الرياضيات".
And today, I want to show you one of those musical notes,
واليوم، أريد أن أريكم واحدة من تلك الملاحظات الموسيقية،
a number so beautiful, so massive,
عدد جميل جداً، ضخم جداً،
I think it will blow your mind.
وأعتقد أنه سيفجر عقلك.
Today we're going to talk about prime numbers.
اليوم سنتحدث عن الإعداد الأولية.
Most of you I'm sure remember that six is not prime
أنا متأكد أن معظمكم يتذكر أن ستة ليس من الأعداد الأولية
because it's 2 x 3.
لأنه 2 × 3.
Seven is prime because it's 1 x 7,
سبعة هو عدد أولي لأنه 1 × 7،
but we can't break it down into any smaller chunks,
ولكن لا يمكننا كسرها نزولا إلى أي أعداد أصغر
or as we call them, factors.
أو كما نسميها، العوامل.
Now a few things you might like to know about prime numbers.
الآن عدد قليل من الأشياء قد تريد أن تعرفونها حول الإعداد الأولية.
One is not prime.
واحد ليس عدد أولي.
The proof of that is a great party trick
الدليل على ذلك خدعة كبيرة
that admittedly only works at certain parties.
ومن المعترف به أن يعمل فقط مع بعض الأعداد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Another thing about primes, there is no final biggest prime number.
وشيء آخر حول الإعداد الأولية، لا يوجد أي عدد نهائي أولي.
They keep going on forever.
إنها تستمر إلى الأبد.
We know there are an infinite number of primes
ونحن نعلم أن هناك عدد لا نهائي من الإعداد الأولية
due to the brilliant mathematician Euclid.
سبب ذلك عالم الرياضيات الرائع إقليدس.
Over thousands of years ago, he proved that for us.
على مدى آلاف السنين، أثبت هذا لنا.
But the third thing about prime numbers,
ولكن الشيء الثالث حول الأرقام الأولية،
mathematicians have always wondered,
علماء الرياضيات يتسائلون دوماً
well at any given moment in time,
في أي لحظة تتوفر لهم في حياتهم
what is the biggest prime that we know about?
ماهو أكبر عدد أولي نعرفه؟
Today we're going to hunt for that massive prime.
اليوم نحن سنصطاد هذا العدد الأولي الكبير
Don't freak out.
لا تخافوا.
All you need to know, of all the mathematics
كل ما تحتاج إلى معرفته في الرياضيات كلها!
you've ever learned, unlearned, crammed, forgotten,
أن ما تعلمته في أي وقت مضى، لم تتعلمه، كثير، نسيته،
never understood in the first place,
لم يفهم أساساً،
all you need to know is this:
كل ما تحتاج إلى معرفته هو هذا :
When I say 2 ^ 5,
عندما أقول 2 ^ 5،
I'm talking about five little number twos next to each other
أنا أتحدث عن حوالي خمس أعداد صغيرة , وعدد اثنين من الرقم (2) بجوار بعضها البعض
all multiplied together,
كلها تتضاعف سوية
2 x 2 x 2 x 2 x 2.
2 × 2 × 2 × 2 × 2.
So 2 ^ 5 is 2 x 2 = 4,
لذلك 2 ^ 5 هو 2 × 2 = 4،
8, 16, 32.
8، 16، 32.
If you've got that, you're with me for the entire journey. Okay?
إذا فهمت هذا، فأنت معي في الرحلة كلها. حسنا؟
So 2 ^ 5,
2 ^ 5،
those five little twos multiplied together.
ضرب تلك الاعداد الخمسة المكونة من العدد (2).
(2 ^ 5) - 1 = 31.
(2 ^ 5)-1 = 31.
31 is a prime number, and that five in the power
31 هو عدد اولي، والخمسة هي محل القوة
is also a prime number.
أيضا عدد أولي.
And the vast bulk of massive primes we've ever found
والغالبية العظمى من الأعداد الأولية التي وجدناها حتى الأن
are of that form:
بهذا الشكل:
two to a prime number, take away one.
اثنين لعدد أولي، يسلب واحد.
I won't go into great detail as to why,
ولن أخوض في تفاصيل كثيرة عن السبب،
because most of your eyes will bleed out of your head if I do,
لأن معظم عينيك سوف تنزف من دماغك إذا فعلت،
but suffice to say, a number of that form
ولكن يكفي أن نقول، عدد من هذا النموذج
is fairly easy to test for primacy.
من السهل نسبيا اختباره كشكل أولي.
A random odd number is a lot harder to test.
عدد فردي عشوائي يتطلب الكثير من الجهد لاختباره.
But as soon as we go hunting for massive primes,
ولكن بمجرد أن نصطاد الإعداد الأولية الضخمة،
we realize it's not enough
سندرك أنه لا يكفي
just to put in any prime number in the power.
فقط وضع أي عدد أولي في محل القوة.
(2 ^ 11) - 1 = 2,047,
(2 ^ 11)-1 = 2,047،
and you don't need me to tell you that's 23 x 89.
ولا تحتاج مني أن أقول لكم أنها 23 × 89.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But (2 ^ 13) - 1, (2 ^ 17) - 1
ولكن (2 ^ 13)--1، (2 ^ 17)--1
(2 ^ 19) - 1, are all prime numbers.
(2 ^ 19)--1، هي جميع الإعداد الأولية.
After that point, they thin out a lot.
بعد هذه النقطة، هي منتشرة بشكل كبير.
And one of the things about the search for massive primes
ومن الأمور حول البحث عن الإعداد الأولية الضخمة
that I love so much is some of the great mathematical minds
هو أنا أحب كثيراً بعض العقول الرياضية الكبيرة
of all time have gone on this search.
الذي قضى وقته كله للبحث.
This is the great Swiss mathematician Leonhard Euler.
هذا هو عالم الرياضيات السويسري العظيم ليونارد إيولر .
In the 1700s, other mathematicians said
في القرن الثامن عشر، قال علماء الرياضيات الآخرين
he is simply the master of us all.
وهو ببساطة سيد لنا جميعا.
He was so respected, they put him on European currency
كانو يحترمونه جداً، ووضعوه على العملة الأوروبية
back when that was a compliment.
هذا عندما كانت تعتبر مجاملة مجاملة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Euler discovered at the time the world's biggest prime:
اكتشف أويلر في ذاك الوقت أكبر عدد أولي في العالم:
(2 ^ 31) - 1.
(2 ^ 31)--1.
It's over two billion.
وهو ما يزيد على 2 بیلیون.
He proved it was prime with nothing more
أثبت أنه كان عدد أولي بأشياء لا تتجاوز كونها
than a quill, ink, paper and his mind.
ريشة، وحبر والورق وعقله.
You think that's big.
تعتقد أن هذا شيء كبير.
We know that (2 ^ 127) - 1
نحن نعلم أن (2 ^ 127)--1
is a prime number.
هو عدد أولي.
It's an absolute brute.
هذا ظلم مطلق.
Look at it here: 39 digits long,
ننظر هنا: 39 أرقام طويلة،
proven to be prime in 1876
أثبتت أنها أعداد أولية في عام 1876
by a mathematician called Lucas.
اكتشفها عالم رياضيات يدعى لوكاس.
Word up, L-Dog.
أتفق معك يا ال دوق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But one of the great things about the search for massive primes,
لكن واحدة من الأشياء العظيمة في البحث عن الإعداد الأولية الضخمة،
it's not just finding the primes.
هو ليس فقط إيجاد الإعداد الأولية.
Sometimes proving another number not to be prime is just as exciting.
في بعض الأحيان إثبات عدد آخر لايكون عدد أولي شيء مثير.
Lucas again, in 1876, showed us (2 ^ 67) - 1,
لوكاس مرة أخرى، في عام 1876، أظهر لنا (2 ^ 67)--1،
21 digits long, was not prime.
رقم بطول 21 رقم، لم يكن عدد أولي.
But he didn't know what the factors were.
ولكنه قال أنه لا يعرف ما العوامل.
We knew it was like six, but we didn't know
كنا نعرف أنه كان مثل ستة، ولكن لم نكن نعرف
what are the 2 x 3 that multiply together
ما هو 2 × 3 التي تتكاثر معا
to give us that massive number.
لتعطينا هذا العدد الهائل.
We didn't know for almost 40 years
لم نكن نعرف لما يقرب من 40 عاماً
until Frank Nelson Cole came along.
حتى جاء "فرانك نيلسون كول" .
And at a gathering of prestigious American mathematicians,
وفي تجمع لعلماء الرياضيات الأمريكية المرموقين،
he walked to the board, took up a piece of chalk,
مشى للسبورة، وتناول قطعة من الطباشير،
and started writing out the powers of two:
وبدأ في كتابة قوى الرقم اثنين:
two, four, eight, 16 --
أثنان , أربعة , ثمانية , 16
come on, join in with me, you know how it goes --
هيا، انضموا إلي، أنتم تعرفون البقية -
32, 64, 128, 256,
32، 64، 128، 256،
512, 1,024, 2,048.
512، 1,024، 2,048.
I'm in geek heaven. We'll stop it there for a second.
أنا في سماء الهوس. نحن سوف نتوقف بعد ثواني.
Frank Nelson Cole did not stop there.
فرانك نيلسون كول لم يتوقف هناك.
He went on and on
وأستمر أكثر فأكثر
and calculated 67 powers of two.
وقوى 67 محسوب من اثنين.
He took away one and wrote that number on the board.
أخذ الرقم واحد وكتب هذا العدد على اللوحة.
A frisson of excitement went around the room.
رعشة إثار جابت أنحاء الغرفة.
It got even more exciting when he then wrote down
أصبح الموضوع أكثر إثارة عندما كتب بعد ذلك
these two large prime numbers in your standard multiplication format --
هذان العددان الكبيران الأوليان في التنسيق البدائي للضرب-
and for the rest of the hour of his talk
وفي بقية ساعة حديثه
Frank Nelson Cole busted that out.
فرانك نيلسون كول ضبطها.
He had found the prime factors
وقد وجد أن العوامل الرئيسية
of (2 ^ 67) - 1.
من (2 ^ 67)--1.
The room went berserk --
هاجت الغرفة
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)-
as Frank Nelson Cole sat down,
عندما جلس "فرانك نيلسون كول"،
having delivered the only talk in the history of mathematics
بعد تسليمه الحديث الوحيد في تاريخ الرياضيات
with no words.
بدون كلمات.
He admitted afterwards it wasn't that hard to do.
واعترف بعد ذلك أنه لم يكن من الصعب أن تفعل ذلك.
It took focus. It took dedication.
يحتاج تركيز. يحتاج تفاني.
It took him, by his estimate,
لقد استغرق الأمر منه، حسب تقديره،
"three years of Sundays."
"ثلاث سنوات من يوم الأحد".
But then in the field of mathematics,
لكن في ميدان الرياضيات،
as in so many of the fields that we've heard from in this TED,
كما هو الحال في الكثير من الحقول التي سمعناها هنا في تيد،
the age of the computer goes along and things explode.
عصر الكمبيوتر يواصل السير وتنفجر الأمور.
These are the largest prime numbers we knew
هذه الأعداد الأولية الأكبر, ونحن على علم
decade by decade, each one dwarfing the one before
قرن بقرن، كل شخص يتجاوز الذي قبله
as computers took over and our power to calculate
كما حلت محلنا أجهزة الكمبيوتر وأخذت قوتنا في الحساب
just grew and grew.
فقط نما ونما.
This is the largest prime number we knew in 1996,
وهذا هو أكبر عدد أولي عرفناه في عام 1996،
a very emotional year for me.
عام مليء بالعواطف بالنسبة لي.
It was the year I left university.
وهذا هو العام الذي تركت فيه الجامعة.
I was torn between mathematics and media.
أنا كنت ممزق بين الرياضيات والإعلام.
It was a tough decision. I loved university.
لقد كان قرارا صعباً. أنا أحب الجامعة.
My arts degree was the best nine and a half years of my life.
درجتي في الفنون كانت أفضل 9 سنوات ونصف في حياتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I came to a realization about my own ability.
ولكن جئت لتحقيق قدرتي الخاصة بي.
Put simply, in a room full of randomly selected people,
ببساطة، في غرفة كاملة من الناس المختارين عشوائياً،
I'm a maths genius.
أنا عبقري رياضيات.
In a roomful of maths Ph.Ds,
في داخل غرفة تغص بحاملي الدكتوراة في الرياضيات
I'm as dumb as a box of hammers.
أنا غبي كما هو صندوق المطارق.
My skill is not in the mathematics.
مهارتي ليست في الرياضيات.
It is in telling the story of the mathematics.
بل في رواية قصة الرياضيات.
And during that time, since I've left university,
وخلال ذلك الوقت، ومنذ ذلك الحين قد تركت الجامعة،
these numbers have got bigger and bigger,
وقد أصبحت هذه الأرقام أكبر وأكبر،
each one dwarfing the last,
كل واحد يتعدى آخر،
until along came this man, Dr. Curtis Cooper,
حتى جاء هذا الرجل، الدكتور كورتيس كوبر،
who a few years ago held the record for the largest ever prime,
الذي سجل قبل بضع سنوات أكبر عدد أولي من أي وقت مضى،
only to see it snatched away by a rival university.
فقط ليراها يتم انتزاعها بواسطة جامعة منافسة.
And then Curtis Cooper got it back.
ومن ثم كورتيس كوبر حصل عليها مرة أخرى.
Not years ago, not months ago, days ago.
ليس قبل سنوات، ولا قبل أشهر، منذ أيام.
In an amazing moment of serendipity,
في لحظة صدفة مذهلة،
I had to send TED a new slide
واضطررت إلى إرسال تيد شريحة جديدة
to show you what this guy had done.
لتظهر لكم ما قام به هذا الرجل.
I still remember -- (Applause) --
وما زلت أذكر
I still remember when it happened.
ما زلت أتذكر عندما حدث ذلك.
I was doing my breakfast radio show.
كنت أقوم ببرنامج إذاعي صباحي
I looked down on Twitter. There was a tweet:
تصفحت تويتر. وكانت هناك تغريدة:
"Adam, have you seen the new largest prime number?"
"آدم، هل رأيت أكبر عدد جديد من الأعداد الأولية"
I shivered --
أنا تجمدت-
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)-
contacted the women who produced my radio show out in the other room,
اتصلت بالنساء المنتجين لبرنامجي الإذاعي في الغرفة الأخرى،
and said "Girls, hold the front page.
وقلت "يا فتيات، كونوا على الصفحة الأولى.
We're not talking politics today.
لن نتحدث عن السياسة اليوم.
We're not talking sport today.
ولن نتحدث عن الرياضة اليوم.
They found another megaprime."
لقد وجدوا عدد أولي كبير آخر. "
The girls just shook their heads,
البنات فقط هزوا رؤوسهم،
put them in their hands, and let me go my own way.
وضعتها في أيديهم، وسمحوا لي أن اذهب في طريقي .
It's because of Curtis Cooper that we know,
وبسبب كورتيس كوبر الذي نعرفه،
currently the largest prime number we know,
حاليا أكبر عدد أولي نحن نعلمه،
is 2 ^ 57,885,161.
هو 2 ^ 57,885,161.
Don't forget to subtract the one.
لا ننسى أن نطرح واحد.
This number is almost 17 and a half million digits long.
هذا العدد تقريبا 17 ونصف مليون أرقام طويلة.
If you typed it out on a computer and saved it as a text file,
إذا قمت بكتابته خارجاً على جهاز كمبيوتر وحفظه كملف نصي،
that's 22 meg.
هذا هو 22 ميج.
For the slightly less geeky of you,
لإخراج العبقري المهووس منكم
think about the Harry Potter novels, okay?
فكروا بروايات هاري بوتر، حسنا؟
This is the first Harry Potter novel.
وهذه هي أول رواية هاري بوتر.
This is all seven Harry Potter novels,
هذه هي جميع روايات هاري بوتر السبعة،
because she did tend to faff on a bit near the end.
لأنها تميل إلى فاف على قليلاً بالقرب من النهاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Written out as a book, this number would run
كتب ككتاب، أن تشغيل هذا العدد
the length of the Harry Potter novels and half again.
طول روايات هاري بوتر ونصف مرة أخرى.
Here's a slide of the first 1,000 digits of this prime.
هنا شريحة من أول 1000 رقم من هذا العدد الأولي
If, when TED had begun, at 11 o'clock on Tuesday,
إذا، من بداية TED، الساعة 11 ص يوم الثلاثاء،
we'd walked out and simply hit one slide every second,
قد نخرج ونضرب ببساطة شريحة واحدة في كل ثانية،
it would have taken five hours to show you that number.
سيكون بالإمكان أن تأخذ خمس ساعات لتظهر لكم هذا الرقم
I was keen to do it, could not convince Bono.
لقد كنت حريصاً على القيام بذلك، لا يمكن أن تقنع بونو.
That's the way it goes.
هذه هي الطريقة التي ستسير عليها الأمور.
This number is 17 and a half thousand slides long,
هذا الرقم هو 17 ونصف ألف شريحة طويلة
and we know it is prime as confidently
ونحن نعرف أنه عدد أولي بكل ثقة
as we know the number seven is prime.
كما نعلم العدد سبعة هو عدد أولي.
That fills me with almost sexual excitement.
أنه يملء معظمي إثارة جنسية.
And who am I kidding when I say almost?
ومن سأمزح معه إذا قلت معظم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I know what you're thinking:
أنا أعرف ما تفكرون به:
Adam, we're happy that you're happy,
آدم، نحن سعداء أن كنت سعيداً،
but why should we care?
ولكن لماذا ينبغي لنا أن نهتم؟
Let me give you just three reasons why this is so beautiful.
اسمحوا لي أن أقدم لكم فقط ثلاثة أسباب لماذا هي جميلة جداً.
First of all, as I explained, to ask a computer
قبل كل شيء، كما شرحت، أسأل جهاز كمبيوتر
"Is that number prime?" to type it in its abbreviated form,
"هل هو عدد أولي" بكتابتها بشكلها المختصر،
and then only about six lines of code is the test for primacy,
وعن طريق 6 أسطر من الأكواد ستختبر أولية العدد
is a remarkably simple question to ask.
سؤال بسيط ملحوظ ليسأل
It's got a remarkably clear yes/no answer,
فقد حصل بشكل ملحوظ وواضح اجابة نعم/لا،
and just requires phenomenal grunt.
ويتطلب فقط نّخر هائل.
Large prime numbers are a great way of testing
الإعداد الأولية الكبيرة طريقة رائعة لاختبار
the speed and accuracy of computer chips.
سرعة ودقة رقائق الكمبيوتر.
But secondly, as Curtis Cooper was looking for that monster prime,
لكن ثانيا، وكما كورتيس كوبر كان يبحث عن ذلك الوحش العدد الأولي،
he wasn't the only guy searching.
أنه لم يكن الرجل الوحيد الذي يبحث.
My laptop at home was looking through
جهازي المحمول كان يبحث أيضاً
four potential candidate primes myself
أربعة اعداد مرشحة لأن تكون أعداد أولية
as part of a networked computer hunt around the world
كجزء من عملية مطاردة شبكات كمبيوتر العالم
for these large numbers.
لهذه الإعداد الكبيرة.
The discovery of that prime is similar to the work
اكتشاف أن العدد الأولي مماثل للعمل
people are doing in unraveling RNA sequences,
لما يفعل الناس في كشف تسلسل الحمض النووي الريبي،
in searching through data from SETI and other astronomical projects.
في البحث من خلال البيانات من سيتي وغيرها من المشاريع الفلكية.
We live in an age where some of the great breakthroughs
أننا نعيش في عصر حيث بعض الإنجازات العظيمة
are not going to happen in the labs or the halls of academia
لن يحدث في المعامل أو قاعات الأوساط الأكاديمية
but on laptops, desktops,
بل على أجهزة الكمبيوتر المحمول، أجهزة الكمبيوتر المكتبية
in the palms of people's hands
على راحة ايدي الناس
who are simply helping out for the search.
نحن ببساطة سنساعد في البحث
But for me it's amazing because it's a metaphor
ولكن بالنسبة لي أنها مذهلة لأنها كناية
for the time in which we live,
للزمن الذي نعيش فيه،
when human minds and machines can conquer together.
متى يمكن قهر العقول البشرية والآلات معا.
We've heard a lot about robots in this TED.
لقد سمعنا الكثير عن الروبوتات هنا في تيد.
We've heard a lot about what they can and can't do.
لقد سمعنا الكثير حول ما يمكنهم وما لا يمكنهم القيام به.
It is true, you can now download onto your smartphone
هذا صحيح، يمكنك الآن تحميل على الهاتف الذكي
an app that would beat most grandmasters at chess.
تطبيق سوف يتغلب على معظم العباقرة في الشطرنج.
You think that's cool.
تعتقد أن هذا رائع.
Here's a machine doing something cool.
هناك شيء رائع الالات تستطيع فعله
This is the CubeStormer II.
وهذا هو كوبيستورمير الثاني.
It can take a randomly shuffled Rubik's Cube.
يمكن أن يستغرق مكعب روبيك تعديلاً عشوائياً.
Using the power of the smartphone,
باستخدام قوة الهاتف الذكي،
it can examine the cube and solve the cube
فإنه يمكن دراسة المكعب وحل المكعب
in five seconds.
في خمس ثوان.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
That scares some people. That excites me.
هذا يخيف بعض الناس. وهو يثيرني.
How lucky are we to live in this age
كم نحن محظوظين ونحن نعيش في هذا العصر
when mind and machine can work together?
عندما العقل والآله يمكنهما العمل معا؟
I was asked in an interview last year in my capacity
طلب مني عمل مقابلة العام الماضي بصفتي
as a lower-case "c" celebrity in Australia,
كطبقة "ج" المتدنية من المشاهير في أستراليا،
"What was your highlight of 2012?"
"ما هو اكتشافك في عام 2012؟"
People were expecting me to talk about
الناس كانوا يتوقعون مني أن أتحدث عن
my beloved Sydney Swans football team.
فريقي المحبوب لكرة القدم "سدني سوانز".
In our beautiful, indigenous sport of Australian football,
الرياضة التقليدية والجميلة لدينا في استراليا هي كرة القدم
they won the equivalent of the Super Bowl.
فازوا بما يعادل "سوبر السلطانية".
I was there. It was the most emotional, exciting day.
كنت هناك. وكان اليوم الأكثر عاطفة واثارة.
It wasn't my highlight of 2012.
لم يكن اكتشافي لعام 2012.
People thought it might have been an interview I'd done on my show.
الناس يعتقدون انها ربما ستكون مقابلة شخصية استطيع ان اقدمها في برنامجي
It might have been a politician. It might have been a breakthrough.
قد يكون سياسيا. ربما يكون إنجازا.
It might have been a book I read, the arts. No, no, no.
ربما يكون كتاب قرأته، فنون. لا، لا، لا.
It might have been something my two gorgeous daughters had done.
أنه ربما كان شيئا فعلته لي ابنتان لي رائعتان.
No, it wasn't. The highlight of 2012, so clearly,
لا، لم يكن. اكتشافي لعام 2012، بشكل واضح،
was the discovery of the Higgs boson.
كان اكتشاف بوزون هيغز.
Give it up for the fundamental particle
حيوا الأداة الاساسية
that bequeaths all other fundamental particles their mass.
والذي سيترك كل الادوات الاساسية الاخرى مقدارهم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And what was so gorgeous about this discovery was
وما كان رائع جداً حول هذا الاكتشاف
50 years ago Peter Higgs and his team
قبل 50 عاماً بيتر هيغز وفريقه
considered one of the deepest of all questions:
أعتبروا سؤال أعمق من جميع الأسئلة:
How is it that the things that make us up have no mass?
كيف تكون الاشياء التي انشئتنا بدون كتلة؟
I've clearly got mass. Where does it come from?
واضح جداً أني أملك كتلة. من أين جاءت ؟
And he postulated a suggestion
وافترض اقتراح
that there's this infinite, incredibly small field
أن هذا الشيء اللامحدود، الصغير بشكل لا يصدق
stretching throughout the universe,
يمتد في جميع أنحاء الكون،
and as other particles go through those particles
وكما تذهب الجزيئات الأخرى من خلال تلك الجسيمات
and interact, that's where they get their mass.
والتفاعل، ومن هناك حصلت على كتلتها.
The rest of the scientific community said,
بقية المجتمع العلمي يقول
"Great idea, Higgsy.
"فكرة عظيمة، هيجسي.
We've got no idea if we could ever prove it.
لا توجد لدينا أدنى فكرة إذا كان بإمكاننا إثبات هذا
It's beyond our reach."
إنه بعيد المنال ".
And within just 50 years,
وفي غضون 50 عاماً فقط،
in his lifetime, with him sitting in the audience,
في حياته، معه يجلس في الجمهور،
we had designed the greatest machine ever
لقد قمنا بتصميم الجهاز أكبر من أي وقت مضى
to prove this incredible idea
لإثبات هذه الفكرة الهائلة
that originated just in a human mind.
التي نشأت في عقل بشري فقط.
That's what is so exciting for me about this prime number.
وهذا مثير جداً بالنسبة لي حول هذا الرقم الأولي.
We thought it might be there,
كنا نظن أنه قد يكون هناك،
and we went and found it.
وذهبنا ووجدناه.
That is the essence of being human.
هذا هو جوهر الإنسان.
That is what we are all about.
وهذا ما نتكون منه نحن.
Or as my friend Descartes might put it,
أو كما يضعه صديقي ديسكارتس
we think,
نحن نعتقد،
therefore we are.
ولذلك نحن هنا.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)